Guide to the Spokane, Portland and Seattle Railway photographs 1890-1970
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Spokane, Portland, and Seattle Railway photographs
1890-1970
Oregon Historical Society Research Library 1200 SW Park Ave. Portland, OR 97205 libreference@ohs.org https://www.ohs.org/research-and-library/
Spokane, Portland, and Seattle Railway
Org. Lot 78
3 cubic feet 6 document cases
Collection consists of marketing and promotional photographs used by the Spokane, Portland, and Seattle Railway. It includes images of rolling stock, railroad tracks, railroad stations, agriculture, street scenes, and landscapes.
Collection is open for research.
Gift of Burlington Northern Railroad, December 1970 (Lib. Acc. 11760, Photo Acc. 970D001).
Selections from the Spokane, Portland, and Seattle Railway photographs are viewable online in OHS Digital Collections.
The collection is arranged in the following series: Series 1. Regional locations and scenery; Series 2. Railroad properties, personnel, and equipment; Series 3. Non-rail transportation, industry, and recreation; Series 4. Railroad promotional materials.
The Spokane, Portland and Seattle (SP & S) Railway operated rail lines in Oregon and Washington between 1905 and 1970. James J. Hill incorporated the railway in 1905 to connect his two transcontinental railway lines, the Northern Pacific (NP) and Great Northern (GN) railways. The company was initially named the Portland & Seattle Railway, and Spokane was added to the name in 1908. SP & S also oversaw the operation of the Oregon Electric Railway, the Oregon Traction Company, and the Oregon Trunk Railroad. SP & S merged with the Burlington Northern Railroad in 1970.
Collection consists of marketing and promotional photographs used by the Spokane, Portland, and Seattle Railway. Subjects include railroad stations and yards; railroad tracks; rolling stock; train wrecks; railroad bridge construction and maintenance; and railway personnel. There are also photographs of towns and landscapes in Oregon, Washington, and California through which the railroads passed, including images of the construction of the Bonneville Dam, the Columbia River and Columbia River Gorge, the Oregon Coast, Mount Hood, and other mountains and lakes. The collection additionally contains photographs of people engaged in various recreations, including hiking, golfing, skiing, and fishing. There are also photographs relating to agriculture in the Pacific Northwest. Also included is one photograph album containing interior and exterior photographs of the Reserved Seat Coach-Cafe Car of the SP & S Railway in 1939. Many of the photographs in this collection were commissioned specifically for SP & S. Photographers represented in this collection include Kiser Photo Co., Photo-Art Commercial Studios, Angelus Commercial Studio, and Arthur M. Prentiss.
Office records of the Seattle, Portland and Spokane Railway Company donated with this collection were separated to Mss 2018, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
Railroads--Northwest, Pacific--Photographs; Railroad trains--Photographs; Agriculture--Northwest, Pacific--Photographs; Cities and towns--Northwest, Pacific--Photographs; Landscapes--Northwest, Pacific--Photographs
Photographs; Railroads
photographs
Prentiss, A. M. (Arthur M.)
Kiser Photo Co. (Portland, Or.); Photo-Art Commercial Studios (Portland, Or.); Angelus Commercial Studio
- Regional locations and scenery, Series 1
  - Albany, Oregon, 1908-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Images of Oregon Electric Railway station on 5th St. and Lyon St., and community celebration of the opening.
  - Astoria, Oregon, 1845; circa 1927-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Images showing downtown architecture, docks and maritime activity, the Astoria column, and workers. Includes 1 photo reproduction of a drawing of Fort Astoria from 1845.
  - Bend, Oregon, 1900-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Images showing the Pilot Butte Inn, the Shelvin-Hixon plant, residences, and a cave.
  - Bonneville Dam, 1937-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Images include aerial views of planning and construction, completed dam, and salmon.
  - California, 1910-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Images of touristic scenes from various locations including Muir Woods and the Palace Hotel.
  - Cannon Beach, Ecola Park, 1900-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Beach scenes, landscapes, and seascapes.
  - Central Oregon, 1900-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Images showing bird refuges, hills, rivers, lakes, mountains, trees, cliffs and gorges, rocks, springs and waterfowl.
  - Clackamas, Oregon, 1900-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Images of residences, agriculture, military, logging, and fishing.
  - Clark County, Washington, 1900-1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Images of residences and agriculture.
  - Corvallis, Oregon, 1900-1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Images of Oregon Agricultural College (now Oregon State University).
  - Crooked River, Oregon, 1900-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Images of mountains, rocks, and river gorges.
  - Deschutes River, Oregon, 1900-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Images of mountains, rocks, river gorges, riverbanks, rapids, trees, and railroad tracks.
  - Eugene, Oregon, 1900-1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Images of the University of Oregon, the Oregon Electric Railway station, and a parade.
  - Hillsboro, Oregon, 1900-1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Images showing a downtown Hillsboro street scene, an apple orchard, and schoolchildren waiting for a train.
  - Longview, Washington, 1920-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Downtown scenes and an aerial view of the Long-Bell lumber yards.
  - Mineral Springs, Washington, 1900-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Images showing Klickitat and Carson Mineral Springs facilities in Washington.
  - Portland, Oregon, 1900-1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Aerial and street-level views of downtown Portland, including industrial and architectural photos, photo reproductions of architectural drawings and street plans, the interior of consolidated ticket office, roses, and the Portland Rose Festival.
  - Prineville, Oregon, 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Aerial and street-level views of Prineville and Crook County.
  - Salem, Oregon, 1900-1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Countryside and agricultural views, architecture, Oregon Capitol building, and the Oregon State Fair.
  - Seaside, Oregon, 1900-1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Images primarily show beach vacationers, residences, and the Lewis and Clark Salt Works.
  - Spokane, Washington, 1900-1930 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Aerial views of downtown and railyards. Street-level views of garden and cemetery.
  - Vancouver, Washington, 1900-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Industrial scenes.
  - Wilsonville Bridge Construction, Oregon Electric Railway, 1907-1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Images showing construction for the Oregon Electric Wilsonville bridge.
  - Wishram, Washington, 1925-1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Historical monument and plaque, with rail yards and landscape views in background.
  - Identified towns and places, Oregon and Washington, 1900-1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Landscapes and natural, agricultural, and architectural images of various country locations in Oregon and Washington.
  - Scenic - Columbia River, 1900-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    Landcape and nature images from the Columbia River and Gorge.
  - Scenic - Mount Hood, 1899-1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Landscape images, Timberline Lodge, and construction of a gondola cable car system.
  - Scenic - national parks, 1900-1930 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Landscape and tourist images of Crater Lake National Park, Yellowstone National Park, Lake St. Mary, Pollock Mountain, Lake McDermott, McDermott Falls, and Glacier National Park. Portrait of Native American chiefs at Glacier National Park.
  - Scenic - Washington, 1900-1930 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Landscape, architectural, road, and bridge images including near Lewiston and Walla Walla, Washington.
  - Scenic - Oregon, 1900-1930 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Landscape, nature and road images.
  - Unidentified Locations, 1900-1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Landscape, nature, architectural, bridge, and road images.
  - Beaches, 1900-1910 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Seascape, landscape, nature images.
  - Lakes, 1900-1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Landscape and nature images.
  - Mountains and waterfalls, 1900-1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Images showing Mt. Jefferson; Mt. Adams; Rock Creek Falls near Stevenson, Washington; Mt. St. Helens; Spirit Lake; Trout Lake near White Salmon, Washington; the Three Sisters; and the McKenzie River.
- Railroad properties, personnel, and equipment, Series 2
  - Stations and yards, 1890-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Images of rail station architecture, yards, tracks, passengers, and workers.
  - Tracks and scenes, 1900-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
    Landscape images featuring tracks, bridges, construction, and workers.
  - Trains - action, 1890-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Images featuring moving trains and landscapes.
  - Trains - wrecks, 1900-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Images featuring train wrecks, damaged property, and salvage operations.
  - Freight cars - exterior, 1900-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Images of freight cars, with rail company logos and marks, workers, and freight items.
  - Locomotives - boiler and tender, 1930-1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Locomotives - diesel and steam, 1890-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Images of locomotives, rail stations, yards, workers, logos and marks.
  - Locomotives - steam, diesel, passenger, freight, 1900-1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Images of locomotives, rail stations, yards, workers, passengers, logos and marks.
  - Oregon Electric Railway, 1910-1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Images of tracks, cars, and signals depot.
  - Passenger cars - exterior, 1900-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Images of rail cars, stations, passengers, logos and marks.
  - Passenger cars - interior, 1900-1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Images featuring passengers, attendants, first-class seats and lounges, coach seats, dining and sleeping cars.
  - People - miscellaneous railroad personnel, 1900-1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Group and individual portaits and candid images of executives, secretaries, and other workers, mainly office and urban settings.
  - Railroad and bridge - construction and maintenance, 1890-1960 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Images of rail construction. Bridges, tracks, scaffolding, cranes, bulldozers, tractors, landscapes, workers.
  - Railroad - shops and yards, 1900-1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Interior views of rail yard industrial spaces. Workers, machinery, architecture, cars and locomotives.
- Non-rail transportation, industry, and recreation, Series 3
  - Agricultural exhibitions, 1900-1930 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Exhibition displays of agricultural products from Oregon and Washington.
  - Agriculture - farming, farm produce, farmhouses, 1900-1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Images of crop fields, farmhouses, agricultural activities, landscapes.
  - Agriculture - hops, berries, etc., 1900-1930 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Images of crop rows and fields of hops and berries, agricultural workers.
  - Agriculture - irrigation, 1900-1930 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Images of outdoor irrigation ditches and construction, and construction engineers.
  - Agriculture - orchards, 1900-1930 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Images of orchards, apples, landscapes, workers.
  - Agriculture - livestock, poultry, etc., 1900-1930 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Images of cattle, poultry, sheep, landscapes, ranches, pens, workers.
  - Agriculture - wheat fields, hay harvesting, etc., 1900-1930 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Images of wheat fields, landscapes, hay bales.
  - Buses, 1900-1930 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Images of vehicles, passengers, and landscapes.
  - Fishing, hunting, camping, hiking, climbing, 1900-1940 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Outdoor sports and recreation, landscape and nature images.
  - Forest, lumber, 1900-1940 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Nature and landscape images, trees, lumber, roads, truck and river log transport.
  - Golf, golfers, and golf courses, 1900-1940 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Lighthouses and coastal landscapes, 1900-1930 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ships and boats, 1900-1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Images of vessels, rivers, St. Johns Bridge, downtown Portland waterfront. Includes Peter Iredale, Battleship Oregon, and the U.S.S. Portland.
  - Great Northern cruise ship and crew, 1915-1917 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Horses, 1910-1950 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Railroad promotional materials, Series 4
  - Promotional materials, 1900-1970 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Images of advertising on posters, murals, billboards.
  - Reserved seat coach-cafe car photograph album, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    "S.P. & S. Ry. Reserved seat coach-café car, nos. 558 & 559, remodeled at Nor. Pac. Como Shops, St. Paul, Minn., April 1939." Passenger car interior and exterior.